Register of the R. V. Polchaninov Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
R. V. Polchaninov papers
1941-2000
2001C14
Hoover Institution Archives
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet) >
Writings, correspondence, and printed matter, relating to the Russian scouting movement.
Polchaninov, R. V.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
R. V. Polchaninoff was born on 27 January 1919 in Novocherkassk, Russia, where his father served on the staff of the Commander-in-Chief of the White Army. He was evacuated with his family from Sevastopol to Constantinople (Istanbul) in November 1920, finally settling in Yugoslavia. There Polchaninoff finished his schooling and began studies in the law department of the University of Belgrade.
At the same time, he was active in the scouting movement, joining the Yugoslav Boy-Scouts in 1931, and later the Russian émigré Boy-Scouts and Sokols. During the Second World War, he was one of the leaders of the Russian underground Scouting movement. At the end of the war he organized a Russian émigré Boy-Scout unit in Niedersachswerfen (near Nordhausen, Germany) just days after the U.S. army liberated the town (11 April 1945). He continued this work among both Russian and Yugoslav displaced persons throughout the immediate post-war years.
In 1951, Polchaninoff settled in the United States, where he continued his scouting work, as well as taught in parochial schools and worked for Radio Liberty (from 1967 to 1983). He also wrote articles for American and émigré newspapers and journals, and published books and bulletins, as well as textbooks for parochial schools.
Chronology
1919 January 27 Born, Novocherkassk, Russia
1920 Evacuated to Yugoslavia
1922-1942 Resident of Sarajevo, Yugoslavia
1931 Joins Russian Boy Scouts
1943 Marries Vlaentina Petrovna Naumova while working in Pskov Orthodox Mission, Pskov, Russia
1951 Arrives in the United States
1981 Commences publishing Letopis' russkikh zarubezhnykh periodicheskikh izdanii
Scope and Content Note
Rostislav V. Polchaninov was a prominent figure in the Russian scouting movement in exile. This collection contains his correspondence, writings and subject files, mostly connected to the Russian Boy Scouts and collecting Russian stamps.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Boy Scouts.; Na't'sional'na'i'a organiza't'si'i'a russkikh razvedchikov.; Russia.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1941-1999 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Clippings and identity papers, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1948-2000 (Box 1)
  Letters, arranged alphabetically by correspondent
- Writings, 1963-1995 (Box 1)
  Newspaper columns and catalog, arranged chronologically by title
- Russian Boy Scouts File, 1951-2000 (Box 1)
  Orders, bulletins and leaflets
- Printed Matter, 1948-2000 (Box 1)
  Bulletins and leaflets
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1941-1999 (Box 1)
  - Clippings about Polchaninov (Folder 1: 1)
  - Identity papers (Folder 1: 2)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1948-2000
  - General, 1996-2000 (Folder 1: 3)
    Circulars to friends
  - Museum of Russian Culture, 1948-2000 (Folder 1: 4)
- WRITINGS, 1963-1995
  - "Razvedcheskaia pochta," catalog of Russian émigré Boy Scout stamps, 1963 (Folder 1: 5)
    Typescript.
  - Newspaper columns, 1977-1995 (Folder 1: 6)
- RUSSIAN BOY SCOUTS FILE, 1951-2000 (Folder 1: 7)
  Includes bulletins and orders of various branches and sub-groups of the Russian émigré scouting movement, some of them edited or published by Polchaninov
- PRINTED MATTER, 1948-2000 (Folder 1: 8)
  Includes leaflets and bulletins edited and issued by Polchaninov, primarily relating to Russian émigré serials, collectibles, and art